<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Perez Uzza, Or, A serious letter sent to Master Edm. Calamy, January the 17th, 1663 touching his sermon at Aldermanbvry, December the 28th, intimating his close design, and dangerous insinuation against the publick peace : with some queries he is to answer, for the satisfaction of the world.</title>
            <author>Udall, O.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64639</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing U17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23555</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12072915</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12072915</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53521</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64639)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53521)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 584:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Perez Uzza, Or, A serious letter sent to Master Edm. Calamy, January the 17th, 1663 touching his sermon at Aldermanbvry, December the 28th, intimating his close design, and dangerous insinuation against the publick peace : with some queries he is to answer, for the satisfaction of the world.</title>
                  <author>Udall, O.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for George Bisaker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: O. Udall.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Calamy, Edmund, 1600-1666. --  Eli trembling for fear of the Ark.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53521:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53521:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>PEREZ <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ZZA.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or, A SERIOUS LETTER Sent To Maſter Edm. Calamy January the 17th 1663, TOUCHING HIS SERMON AT ALDERMANBVRY, December the 28th, Intimating his <hi>Cloſe Deſign,</hi> and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Inſinuation</hi> againſt the Publick Peace; with ſome <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> he is to <hi>Anſwer,</hi> for the <hi>Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> of the <hi>World.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Nulla CONCIONE excitatum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> quis Novit.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Tully Orat.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>George Biſaker,</hi> 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:53521:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53521:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PEREZ <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ZZA.</hi> OR, A SERIOUS LETTER Sent to Maſter <hi>EDM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ND CALAMY</hi> January the 17th 1663, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Iſhop <hi>Ridley,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Latimer,</hi> two good Men, good Biſhops, godly reformers, and holy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs (O Sir, Biſhops were em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by the Lord as <hi>Inſtruments</hi> to deliver us from Popery, and (which I never heard any of their adverſarles did) freely offered themſelves as <hi>Martyrs</hi> againſt Popery) could not <hi>agree</hi> in the <hi>way,</hi> though <hi>they were Brethren,</hi> yet they agree in the <hi>end,</hi> though they were <hi>adverſaries.</hi> (O in the end all ſober, modeſt and, pious diſſenters in the World will be of one heart, of one mind; then ſhall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53521:3"/>we ſee a gracious returne of our Saviours prayer; <hi>(&amp; that God heard him in that which he pray'd for:) that all Chriſtians are one in Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh</hi> 17.23.</note> as the Father is in Him, &amp; He in the Father; that they are one in the Father and the Son:</hi> and then the World which by our <hi>many Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> is tempted to an unbeliefe of <hi>all;</hi> will own one pure Religion and undefiled, <hi>and will believe that God ſent Chriſt into the World to teach it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 You and I who never fell out in the way, <hi>but were of one mind in thoſe things</hi> whereunto <hi>we had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready attained; and in other things</hi> waited patiently <hi>untill the Lord revealed them unto us;</hi> in an unhappy va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of opinion, retaining a Chriſtian Unity of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the many things <hi>we</hi> agree in having a greater pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to unite us, then the few things we differ in have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o divide us; ſo that in things <hi>neceſſary</hi> we came up to an holy Uniformity, in things indifferent we retained a Chriſtian liberty: in all things we maintained a Goſpell charity; I ſay you and I who never fell out in the <hi>way,</hi> muſt now differ when we are come within view of that end you <hi>and I look for, you and I haſten unto; (for you muſt, I may:)</hi> I knew indeed you enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained other thoughts then I did, of the ancient, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive, Apoſtolicke and Goſpell Government of the Church; of its pure and decent Worſhip and Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of its decent order and innocent Rites and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies: but I knew withall how to pitty you <hi>as one ſubject to the like infirmities;</hi> as well perſuaded—that we <hi>know but in part,</hi>—that ſomething <hi>will be lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to our Faith;</hi>—that our <hi>God divideth to every one ſeverally as He will a meaſure of the gift of Chriſt;</hi>—as though we <hi>had not already attained,</hi> or <hi>were already perfect but</hi> did <hi>follow after</hi>—I knew you allowed your ſelf another practice of the ſame Religion an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53521:3"/>to your thoughts then I could; and I that <hi>could</hi> come up to the uſe of ſome harmeleſſe things enjoyned <hi>deſpiſed</hi> not you who <hi>could not</hi> as I hope you who <hi>could not</hi> come up to the uſe of them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro</hi> 14.3.</note>
               <note place="margin">☜</note> 
               <hi>judged</hi> not me who <hi>could:</hi>
               <q>I think him happy who alloweth not himſelf the uſe of what he condemneth, and he much happier who condemneth not himſelf <hi>in the uſe of that which he doeth, or may allow:</hi>
               </q> I knew your dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent practice from the grand eſtabliſhment of the Nation rendered you uncapable of thoſe encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which are allowed by no Nation to any that oppoſe its publique conſtitution, (as what Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will <hi>maintaine them</hi> that oppoſe it) I pittyed you now under diſcouragement under this frame of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment which you cannot approve as I hope you would pitty me if I <hi>ſhould be,</hi> and <hi>did pitty</hi> thoſe many Orthodox and good men that <hi>were</hi> under diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment under the frame of Government <hi>you do approve:</hi> when I heard that your conſcience guided by ſome ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular apprehenſions peculiar to thoſe of your way, perſwaded you not to do ſome things which you have done formerly, and think others may do now as things indifferent, decent orderly &amp; harmeleſs enjoyn'd by the power ordained of God over you, which you are to obey for conſcience ſake;
<q>I was ſorry and ſaid, O that any gracious ſoul ſhould ſuffer it ſelf to be ſo inſnared as to be under a ſad neceſſity either of going againſt his conſcience, which is dangerous; or of going againſt Authority;</q> which is ſinfull when I heard that your conſcience guided by the general principles of Chriſtianity where you could not cheerfully obey obliged you patiently to ſuffer; (the truth after God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe in this caſe which good men profeſſed—was this (I <hi>cannot</hi> obey <hi>though I die,</hi> I can <hi>die</hi> rather then diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey) I rejoyced and ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Mr. <hi>Calamy</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſerve
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53521:4"/>
               <q>God paſſively, I muſt ſerve God <hi>actively,</hi> I am ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to glorifie God by <hi>obedience,</hi> he muſt glorifie Him by <hi>patience: even ſo O Father becauſe ſo it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thee.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>When I heard of your meekneſſe and modeſty, your candour and ingenuity, your humanity and charity, your piety and humility under this late diſpenſation which rendred you with the reverend Doctor <hi>Bates,</hi> Doctor <hi>Jacomh,</hi> Doctor <hi>Manton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Watſon,</hi> &amp;c. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent and honourable in their eyes that differ from you,—(<hi>virtus vel in hoſte</hi>—really we pitty what we ſee of man, and we love what we ſee of God in you) I ſaid <hi>cum tales ſint, utinam noſtrj eſſent</hi>—my thoughts ſometimes (for here's more freedome for thoughts in this innocent ſolitude (a Paradiſe in all things, but that here are no Serpents, no temptations,) then in your throug of intereſts, paſſions, and men:) repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you unto me as ſerious as that man in the 10th of St. <hi>Mark</hi>—asking, what ſhall <hi>we do that we may inherit eternall life?</hi> and you are anſwered, honour, reverence, and obey your Superiours, honour Father and Mother; live honeſtly and peaceably with your neighbours: — <hi>defraud not, thou ſhalt not,</hi> &amp;c. You anſwer and ſay—all theſe have we <hi>endeavoured to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve from our youth;</hi> as it was ſaid of our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour there, that beholding the Man, he loved him, &amp;c. ſo I ſeriouſly reflecting upon you, cannot chooſe but <hi>love</hi> you, onely one thing you lack: —
<q>O go your way, part with all the eſteem, reputation, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt you have gained, and devote it to the publick welfare and peace of Chriſtendome:</q> — Have you liberty to do or to forbeare ſome indifferent things, O uſe it not (this rich Jewell) for the offence of the weak below, nor the contempt of the ſtrong above you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo as upon the ſame grounds any <hi>man may
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53521:4"/>make it a cloake of maliciouſneſſes</hi> Are you poſſeſſed of the precious Jewell of a tender conſcience? be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded in your own minds apart from all opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, fancy, prejudice, intereſt, what part of the will of God by which you muſt be judged, you and your conſcience, thoſe things you ſcruple at are againſt? what forbids white any more than black Garments, kneeling any more then ſtanding, &amp;c. If they are againſt no Law, every one of them apart, how are they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a tender conſcience that hath alwayes an eye upon a Law, (and peace be upon them that walk ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this rule) if to read a good Prayer-book be no where forbidden, how is it a ſin; and if it be no ſin, how doth it trouble a tender conſcience: — deny your ſelves — and you ſhall have complacency and ſatisfaction enough to your thoughts and wiſhes in Heaven; if you ſhould be as that man, ſad at this ſaying, and goe away grieved; O then ſubmit at leaſt to our Saviours laſt Leſſon to the man, <hi>Take up the Croſſe, and follow Me.</hi>—</p>
            <p>Sometimes I think, (and it's no little pleaſure to obſerve the innocent emanations of our ſouls, and the harmleſſe ſpringing of our thought, pure as the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, cleer as the firſt dawn of day, when we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, with quiet, tranquility, and peace with our God, our conſcience, <hi>and with all the World</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>) ſometimes I think I heare you a sked by ſober men, as <hi>Agrippa</hi> was by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> believe you the Prophets, believe you the Scripture that enjoyes obedience to Magiſtrates, and thoſe under them in Church and State, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, under and peace; do you believe the primitive practiſe of the Church of God lead by the ſpirit of God in all ages; do you believe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Counſels; do you believe the holy ſayings of the Fathers: we know you do believe them, and you
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53521:5"/>conſidering how neer we come to what the Scripture teacheth concerning obedience, decency, and order, and edification; what the Catholick Church, before Popery was heard of, practiſed; — ſay as Mr. <hi>Vines,</hi> &amp;c and others would ſay,— you have almoſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded us to an uniformity, to order, to decency, to obedience; (for if ancient Hiſtory may be believed, and if humane evidence may be of any uſe (which it muſt be of, or elſe we have nothing ſure, for if Laws were not as we are told they are by men, our eſtates are loſt; if deeds are not ſuch as they are witneſſed, our Lands are forfeited; and if we in the World live onely to deceive and be deceived, we are undone—) the Catholick Church before Popery kept up two things that were its glory, uniformity, and ſincere o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience,— and if honeſt and knowing men may be believed, the reformed Churches keep up an unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity among themſelves, and obedience even to their Popiſh Princes—) and methinks I hear the ſober men ſay as Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> we would to God not only <hi>you</hi> but <hi>all Chriſtians this day,</hi> were not only <hi>almoſt</hi> but <hi>alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether</hi> ſuch as we are, except onely our unhappineſſe that we are looked upon as <hi>enthralled</hi> our ſelves, and as thoſe that would <hi>enthrall</hi> others; whereas we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire onely that all men may be free from all <hi>prejudices, intereſt,</hi> and partiality <hi>to know what they ought to do and to do what they know:</hi> we deſire only that Kings may be free to command according to their conſcience; ſubjects may be free to obey according to their <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> and that none may perſwade the World that Kings ſin, commanding what they think in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is good; and that Subjects ſin in doing thoſe things when commanded, which they think in their conſcience are not in themſelves evill.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:53521:5"/>
            <p>As we would all the truths of God were received not in Word but in Power; in the holy ghoſt, and in much aſſurance, ſo we would that great truth of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, which our Religion teacheth with moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, Inforceth with moſt motives, and preſſeth with moſt power of any Religion in the world, <hi>viz.</hi> of obedience and uniformity were owned among us ſo freely that Chriſtian Kings and Princes might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain our Religion as their intereſt, and all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian people might entertain it as their peace, and compoſure. This is all the harm we wiſh; this is all the evil we think, we are thus harmleſſe, thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent in our thoughts towards you: Amidſt theſe pleaſing thoughts of you at once, my duty and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light (that I might not know that undiſturbed calm here below which I look for above) behold an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing meſſage is brought me this week (and I know not by what correſpondence whatever you ſpeak or do is ſuddenly ſpread abroad throughout the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom) that you had 1. In contempt of the authority of a full and free Parliament, which you once cried up as the only power of God ordained in this Nation. 2. To the diſturbance of a quiet Government, under which we began to lead peaceable and quiet lives, in all godlineſſe and honeſty. 3. To the offence of a gracious Soveraign many waies indeared to you. 4. To the grieving of many a poor ſoul which expected you of all men ſhould ſhew a pattern of humility, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and obedience: and the miſleading of more who have that reverence for your perſon, that by your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample may be induced to your miſcarriage, to the great trouble of your <hi>Dtoceſan,</hi> who is hereby in a ſtreight betwixt the ſad choice of either ſeeing you puniſhed, ſo as not becoming a man of your Coat and Order, or of winking at you againſt the grand eſtabliſhment of the preſent Parliament (and <hi>you know what it is to protect delinquents from Juſtice</hi>) you preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I am afraid, by making uſe of that way to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53521:6"/>the people (for it is obſerved that preaching and printing undid) you will provoke the Magiſtrate to do as King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth did, who ordained, that whereby of late by reaſon of certain <hi>controverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſeditious Preachers, his Majeſty out of the love he bare to the quiet of his Subjects, inhibitted all men from preaching in any open audience, unleſſe they were li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenced by the Lord Protector, or my Lords Grace of</hi> Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury; <hi>yea, by bringing the abomination of ſedition that makes deſolate into the holy place, you will make the Magiſtrate as much afraid to open the Church doors to you, as to open</hi> Janus <hi>his Temple, as much afraid to hear the Goſpel as the Iſraelites were to hear the Law:</hi> equal the terrour, the thunder, the fear under both, Chriſtian Princes will look upon Lords daies as daies of <hi>Sabbaoth</hi> of Hoſts, and armies and noiſe than of Sabbath of reſt and peace: and when preachers tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lift up their voices like Trumpets to tell people of their former tranſgreſſion, but to incite them to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit new ones: I am afraid that you call, cauſe men by theſe courſes to abhor the ſervice of God; and ſo by your fault the Word of the <hi>Lord be precious in our daies:</hi> and there be no open viſion: You preached, I hear Mr. <hi>Calamy,</hi> the 28. of <hi>December,</hi> when the Kings thoughts were full of favour towards you, and all your friends were reſolved of obedience and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, that in ſo doing they might put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men, where the Nobility and Gentry had their eyes upon your carriage and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour in order to a further clemency or ſeverity: O Mr. <hi>Calamy, a wiſe man knoweth time and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and the men of <hi>Iſſachar</hi> had <hi>underſtanding in the times;</hi> knowing what <hi>Iſrael ought to do:</hi> O there was a time to <hi>keep ſilence,</hi> and there would have been a time to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>Your Text I hear was, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.13. where me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I no ſooner hear of the Ark, but I call to mind that paſſage, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.6, 7. <hi>And when they came to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53521:6"/>Nachons threſhing floor, Uzzah put forth his hand to the Ark of God, and took hold of it, for the Oxen ſhook it; and the anger of the Lord was kindled againſt Uzzah, and God ſmote him there for his errour.</hi> The Ark may be in danger, and yet you have no call to uphold it; the Ark may ſeem to you in danger unleſs you put your hands to it, and you may be in danger if you meddle with it.</p>
            <p>Now conſider your call; you were there by Law made a hearer, O how durſt you but abide in that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling wherein you were called! Why did not you ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be quiet, and to follow your own buſineſs? and if you muſt ſpeak a word of Exhortation to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, why did you not aſſure them, that you and they muſt needs be obedient to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, and to ſubmit for conſcience ſake! Why did you not deſire them to go home, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what that meaneth: <hi>If the ſpirit of the Ruler riſe up againſt thee, ſtir not out of thy place,</hi> for <hi>yielding pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifieth great offences?</hi> Eccl. 10.4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 1. I hear you obſerved, that the threatnings of the ſecond and third Chapter, and the terrors of the fourth, were denounced and inflicted, <hi>Becauſe he did not reſtrain his wicked ſons from their lewd courſes.</hi> You have given his Majeſty and his Parliament fair warning, to perſiſt in their ſevere reſtraints of all li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſſe, and not to hearken to that indulgence which may be their ruine that they grant it to, and their own that grant it: To indulge men in a wrong way, is to undo them and our ſelves too; Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not ſo firm when it prevariouſly depends upon the private humours of Subjects, as when it is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally eſtabliſhed upon the publick reſolutions of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. An able Prince that would eſtabliſh a troubled Government muſt have two things e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent, power and virtue; he ought to have virtue to preſerve his dignity, and power to check others inſolence; power begets fear, and fear makes Gods,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53521:7"/>and Kings. And really it is high time for diſcipline to awake, when by a ſad liberty offences are grown ſo impudent as to controul it, and ſo potent as to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the ſuppreſſing of it. Oh! <hi>Ely</hi> may beget <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas, Phineas</hi> may beget <hi>Ichabod.</hi> Remiſsneſſe may beget prophaneſs, and prophaneſs may beget the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partare of the glory.</hi> Irreſolution looſens all the joynts of State; a good nature may be a good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion for a private perſon, but for a Prince to be ſo is miſchief to himſelf and others. Remiſsneſs and connivance are the ruine of unſettled Kingdomes. Let us ſatisfie our ſelves in the beſt Principles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Government, and keep cloſe to them, and leave the ſucceſs to God. <hi>Ely</hi> muſt not let his ſons eſcape, nor Magiſtrates their people, with a <hi>why do you theſe things? for</hi> I <hi>hear of your evil dealings by all this people: nay my ſons, for it is no good report that</hi> I <hi>hear.</hi> Upon the whole matter I appeal to your own Conſcience, whether the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of great rules of piety, worſhip, order, and obedience, againſt which no man muſt appear (all men being publickly reſtrained by juſt penalties from ſaying or doing any thing ſcandalous to, or deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from the true Religion, which is eſteemed, and ſo ſettled, the beſt and moſt holy) be not a better way to preſerve the Ark, then to allow looſe men Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to do what they pleaſe ſometime.</p>
            <p>I know you think you may be indulged in your opinions, though <hi>Ely</hi>'s Sons were not to be indulged in their Practiſes:—You know theſe are damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hereſies as well at damnable practiſes; and though I cannot ſay your Opinions are ſuch, yet upon the ſame ground that the Church allowed ſuch Moderate men as you are, Liberty of Conſcience, it muſt allow all men Liberty that can but pretend to Conſcience: Beſides, you have Liberty of Opinion (for the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment takes no notice of your opinions: but you muſt not have Liberty of practiſe, eſpecially where
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53521:7"/>your Practiſes hath been ſuch, that their eares tingle that have heard of it.</p>
            <p>Now ſome there are that would make compariſons between your Practiſes and the Sons of <hi>Ely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sons of <hi>Ely</hi> were ſons of <hi>Belial, i. e.</hi> that endure not the yoak.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They altered the cuſtome, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king too much to themſelves.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And if any one ſaid, Let them not fail to burn of the fat preſently, and thou ſhalt take as much as thy ſoul deſireth; then they would anſwer him, Nay, but we will have it preſently, or we will take it by force.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They made men abhor the Sacrifice of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Would the world did not obſerve of you that you cannot endure <hi>the yoak.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. You altered a Cuſtome in the Church, yea all the Cuſtomes of the Church, and have taken too much upon you.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If any one ſaid unto you, be contented, let the great things of Government and obedience take place, and then you may do what you pleaſe: (for true Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to do good, and good Government, may very well conteſt together) then you an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Nay, but we will take it preſently, or <hi>we will take it by force.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. And you have made men abhor true godlineſs, and ſerious holineſs, becauſe you did ſuch ſtrange things, who uſually pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed it.</p>
            <p>We cannot now own being holy, unleſſe we own a ſuſpicion, at leaſt, of diſloyalty too. O Sir, the good wayes of God have been evil ſpoken of through you, and many a man was afraid of being ſerious, leaſt he ſhould be ſuſpected ſeditious; and many a poor ſoul applauded his very prophaneſſe, becauſe it was loyal and honeſt; and deſpiſed Religion, becauſe he ſaw you made it diſloyal and turbulent. And indeed, give me that Religion that is moſt charitable to all men.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:53521:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 2. I hear you obſerved that the Iſraelites confeſſed <hi>the Lord had ſmitten them:</hi> Though we know all evil of puniſhment is from the Lord; yet we repine at men; we murmur againſt the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate that diſchargeth his Conſcience; we exclaim againſt our Paſtors who perform their duty; we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of Parliaments, who enact according to the publiſhed reaſon: we entertain hard thoughts of the Magiſtrates that execute Juſtice and maintain Truth; whereas if we ſuffer any thing by theſe men perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ſeveral duties, we are to look upon it as the hand of God upon us, and to ſay with old <hi>Ely, It is the Lord, let him do what ſeemeth him good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I <hi>am informed,</hi> that you obſerved, that they thought they were ſafe by the preſence of the Ark, <hi>but therein they were miſerably miſtaken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 3. And I have often obſerved of you and thoſe of your way, that you confine your Religion, Worſhip, Church and ſafety to a few opinions and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, equally modern, which if you can but ſecure, though the Catholick and Apoſtolick Faith, once delivered to the Saints, be indangered, though the publick Worſhip be neglected, though all Order, Diſcipline and Decency be overthrown, though the ancient ſucceſſion of Biſhops, Paſtors, and Miniſters be interrupted, though the Word and Sacraments, that make and ſupport the Church, be laid aſide, you can call the ſaddeſt times that ever we ſaw <hi>Goſpel-times,</hi> and you can ſay, that you enjoy in purity and plenty the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt. But if that new way which Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> in the year 1535. ſet up at <hi>Geneva,</hi> be rejected, as a novelty of an hundred years conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, by thoſe that deſire to live and die in that <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> which hath been practiſed by all good men in all places theſe 1600. years.</p>
            <p>If every Miniſter be no a Biſhop in his own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; If a few ignorant, but devout ſouls, ſhall not bear ſway over all the 1 Neighbours, as Lay-elders,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53521:8"/>admitting whom they pleaſe to, and turning whom they pleaſe <hi>from</hi> the Sacrament: If every man be not at liberty to utter what words he pleaſe before God, and neglect the <hi>wholeſome form of ſound words,</hi> commended by the Church: If a Miniſter muſt wear a <hi>linnen Ephod,</hi> a harmleſs garment. If a man muſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kneel humbly, then ſtand untowardly, in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion to God. If men muſt repent of, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce their former rebellion: If a few trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome men be ſilenced, and if they that oppoſe the Church be not preferred by it; You ſay the Ark is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving; the glory is departing: the ſafety of <hi>Iſrael</hi> indeed was not in the Ark, but in an uniform and conſtant obedience to the eternal Law of God kept in the Ark: and our ſafety lieth not in any peculiar formality, opinion, or in any ſingular perſons, but in a ſincere profeſſion of the ancient Truth that hath upheld the Church in all ages, in all places, and in all conditions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 3. We hear that you ſhould ſay: <hi>That the Ark of the Covenant would not preſerve thoſe that had bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Covenant with God;</hi> no <hi>priviledge</hi> ſecures them that neglect their <hi>duty:</hi> the beſt man that doth as a malefactour muſt ſuffer ſo too. And Sir I pray conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that Religion cannot preſerve you if you live not according to the known principles of Religion, that it, if you in conſcience cannot reſiſt authority, yet ſpeak againſt: if you who have taken an oath to be true to your Governours, will yet oppoſe them, <hi>The word of the Lord came unto me ſaying,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ezekiel, ſay now to the rebellious houſe, that by the keeping the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> that is, your oath of allegiance to the king of <hi>Babylon</hi> (mark it to the heatheniſh king of <hi>Babylon</hi>) and not any Covenant againſt him the kingdome may ſtand: but you <hi>rebelled</hi> againſt him, <hi>i. e.</hi> your King to whom you had ſworn allegiance, ſhall he proſper? ſhall he eſcape that doth ſuch things? or ſhall he break the Covenant, <hi>i. e.</hi> his oath of allegiance to the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53521:9"/>King, and be delivered? In the place that the King liveth (whoſe oath he hath taken) ſaith the Lord to the king of Iſrael) he ſhall dye: the holy diſcipline cannot preſerve them that have broke the oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, the Oath of Supremacy, the oath of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical obedience, and the proteſtation, and all the publick oaths they have taken before God and men. I know you think you have been very tender of the Covenant of God, and of any Covenant you have made with God, I hope you have. But as to that <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant,</hi> I muſt needs ſay: that I think you cannot keep your Covenants with God if you keep it. How can you keep your Covenant before God in the oath of allegiance to the King, if you keep that Covenant by which you <hi>fought</hi> againſt him? How can you keep your Covenant before God in the oath of Supremacy, if you keep this Covenant by which you oppoſe the Kings Supremacy? How can you keep your Covenant before God in the proteſtation you made 1641. to defend Religion, as it was then eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, if you keep that Covenant wherein you ſwear to alter the Religion eſtabliſhed: as the Ark ſecured not them if they kept not their Covenant with God: ſo all the tokens of Gods preſence among you cannot ſecure you if you break your many oaths of allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, Supremacy, Canonical Obedience, Proteſtations made in the preſence of God: nay let me tell you further (for I freely open you my heart) that I doubt no token of Gods preſence, which you may imagine you have among you may ſecure you, if you ſtand to the Covenant you have made againſt the Kings autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and will, whoſe ſubjects you are, againſt the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed way of the Catholick Church members where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of you are: againſt a government of Apoſtolical in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution which hath been continued with ſuch an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, uninterrupted, unqueſtioned ſucceſſion in all the Churches of God in all kingdoms that have been called Chriſtians throughout the world, fifteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53521:9"/>years together againſt all principles and rules of Government. You cannot be ſafe untill you have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely endeavoured to lay aſide all the new humours, opinions, &amp; practices which have been of late brought into the Church, and trouble your ſelves and others no longer with any unquiet ſingularities, but return peaceably, meekly, and humbly to the Communion of the univerſal Church, ſtanding ſoberly in the paths, and ſeriouſly conſidering which is the old way of the people of God in all ages, and walk therein, that you may finde reſt to your ſouls.</p>
            <p>Object. 3. <hi>And Eli ſate,</hi> &amp;c. ſaith the Text: <hi>Eli</hi> you know was his prieſt: for you need not be told that there were firſt Levites, ſecondly prieſts, thirdly higher prieſts among the <hi>Jews,</hi> as there were 1. diſciples, 2. the ſeventy, 3. Apoſtles among the firſt Chriſtians, and then by the Apoſtles inſtitution with univerſal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, 1. Deacons, 2. Prieſts, 3. Biſhops and Arch-Biſhops: among us now, as 1. the people, 2. the Levites, 3. the prieſts did abide in that calling where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they were called, whether the care of their families their own affairs and ſouls, or miniſtry they waited on their miniſtry, or they that teach on teaching, or they that exhort on exhortation, and they by prayer committed publick affairs to the <hi>providence of God, and the care of Governours and Judges,</hi> medling not with things too high for them: Onely the high Prieſt the Governour (for in thoſe daies the Clergy had the care of civill affairs, and the Common-wealth was not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of their excellent worth, parts, and uſefulneſs in government, and the <hi>Jews</hi> having any matter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt others, went not to law before the unjuſt, but before the Saints. And know ye not that we ſhall judge Angels. How much more them of this life. <hi>Eli</hi> I ſay the high Prieſt and Judge who had the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on his ſhoulder ſate in the way, <hi>and trembled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Ark,</hi> his head onely was full of thoughts, his heart onely was full of care for the publick, other
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53521:10"/>poor people <hi>ſtudied to quiet, and to follow their own buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:</hi> So the honeſt people, 2. the Deacons, 3. we the inferiour may ſet our heart at reſt, and leave the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick cares to publick breaſts, wrapping up our ſelves within an innocent privacy, and looking to our ſelves and the flocks, over which the holy Ghoſt hath made us overſeers while our <hi>Elies,</hi> our Prince, our Rulers, our Arch-Biſhops &amp; Biſhops have many ſad thoughts of our Church openly threatned, and ſecretly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the old practices of Papiſts, and the new at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of ſome of the ſeparation, though we here hug our ſelves here in peace, quiet, and great content, committing the world to the care of God and his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and attending onely on that part of it, hereof we have a care, and not without call looking fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>He ſate alone thinking with himſelf</hi> he had that peace within which he wanted abroad, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure and quiet he wiſhed in the kingdome, he enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in himſelf: he went not among the vulgar to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe them againſt the miſgovernment, who were of themſelves apt enough to be untoward and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to ſtir them up to add the miſery of dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick ſedition to a foreign war, here he ſuits and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines his thoughts to his own breaſt, and if any man hath a faith of this nature, <hi>the evidence of things not ſeen,</hi> he ought to have it to himſelf. <hi>Vi more quod ſua natura tranquillum ſit ventorum vi agitari atque tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bori, ſic &amp; populum ſua ſponte placatum hominum ſeditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorum vocibus, ut violentiſſimis tempeſtatibus citari, Tul. Orat. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 14 <hi>ſect.</hi> 46 Really Mr. <hi>Calamy,</hi> I bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed my ſelf in the late calm and ſerenity of the Church after its great ſettlement in Law, when upon a ſudden this attempt of yours raiſed the uſual ſtorms of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, complaint, whiſpering, ſpeaking evil of dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, fears, jealouſies, and diſcontent, and that general diſcompoſure, for which you will be one day ſorry. <hi>When the people hear evil tidings they murmur.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:53521:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 6.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.2. <hi>A Text they ſay quoted by Mr.</hi> Calamy.</note> They ſay you obſerved that the old man was not troubled <hi>what became of his ſons ſo the Ark was ſafe.</hi> O Mr. <hi>Calamy,</hi> if he was ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the Church, as to neglect his own as indeed Mr. <hi>Calamy</hi> we are not to ſeek our own opinion, eſteem, or advantage, but the good of the Church, how much more carefull ought we to be of the Churches peace, in in which our own is involved. <hi>In the peace thereof you ſhall have peace,</hi> how much more carefull ought we to be that we diſturb not the peace of the Church in whoſe trouble we are ſure to be rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. O Sir, if not for our own, yet for our childrens ſake; for alas! what have theſe done: yea for their ſakes that are yet <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, let us follow the things that make for peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He took more care of his children, &amp;c.</hi> O if you will be ſo unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural to your wives and children as to part with their livelihood, and maintenance rather then with your own ſingular opinions and imaginations, learn from your own obſervation of <hi>Eli,</hi> not to diſturb the peace of the Church, that you may come again to a capacity to provide for the neceſſities of your families, then and not till then ſhall I ſee the peace of the Church, when we have all learned to <hi>deny</hi> our ſelves our own wiſdome, honour, and intereſt, and ſeeks his own but all the great things of publick peace and good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 7. I hear you obſerved that the Ark was an holy place for Gods preſence, and now I hope poor ſouls will learn from you if not from us, that ſome things may be holy with a relative holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſo dedicared to an holy ſervice, that they may not be profaned to a common uſe <hi>(what is ſeparated unto God that call not thou common or profane)</hi> and that our God who is every where by his preſence, in heaven by his glory, in hell by his juſtice, in the world by his providence, in the conſciences of men by his law and fear, in the hearts of his people by his grace and Spirit, was in the Ark as you ſay in the Tabernacle and Temple, as the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſaith, is in our Churches too by his preſence and bleſſing. And now I hope you will perſwade your people that theſe places are holy, and that they are no other than the houſes of God, that they may take heed to themſelves when they come to the Houſe of God.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:53521:11"/>
            <p>And as they do well in <hi>keeping the Sahbaths,</hi> times dedicated to God, ſo they would do well in <hi>reverencing the Sanctuaries,</hi> the places devoted to his ſervice. Now I hope Sacriledge may be a ſin and it may be accounted once again a ſin to devour that which is <hi>boly,</hi> and after vows to make enquiry. And I hope none of you will any more repine to ſee the Lord ſerved in the <hi>beauty of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> When you ſay the Ark was holy, I hope you think places of Gods ſpecial manifeſtations of himſelf are holy too, and that we ought to compoſe our ſelves to Reverence in thoſe places where we ſet our ſelves as in the preſence of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 8. <hi>This holy Ark,</hi> you ſaid, (as I am informed) <hi>was the Type of the Church;</hi> for as the Ark, ſo the Church preſerves the Scripture, and is the pillar and ground of truth. And I hope you will hear the Church therefore; and you will teach your people that if they heard not the Church, they are (as the Scripture ſaith) as publicans and ſinners. O Sir, away with all private ſuggeſtions and opinions, and ſubmiſſively yield to the Rules the Church delivers as it delivered the Scripture. If the Church took care to preſerve the Scripture, oh fear not that ſhe will enjoyn any thing contrary to the Scriptures, and if you believe her not for her own ſake, yet believe her for the Scriptures ſake which ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves. Oh charge her not too raſhly with errour, whoſe care (as you ſay) it is to preſerve the <hi>truth;</hi> the Church preſerved the truth five thouſand years before Presbytery was heard of, and it may preſerve them many years more when Presbytery ſhall be heard of no more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 9. <hi>The Ark,</hi> I am told you ſaid, <hi>was a Type of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt;</hi> for as God communicated himſelf then by the Ark, ſo he doth now by the Ordinances. O then why do thoſe of your way ſeparate themſelves from the Ordinances? why are the Congregations in <hi>London</hi> ſo thin as I am told they are? It may be you ſay becauſe their Miniſters are removed into corners. O did they come formerly to hear men, or did they come to hear God? Did they come to hear the Word as it was the word of this or that man, or did they come to hear it as it was and is ſtill the word of God. I hope they did not go to hear men, and if they went to hear what God would ſay unto them, is not he the ſame, as yeſterday, ſo to day as for ever: and granting (though <hi>I</hi> hope
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53521:11"/>you do not think ſo) that Miniſters are now weaker then they were, muſt we hear in faith of mans power, or rather muſt not we hear in the faith of the power of God, whoſe ſtrength is moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent in weakneſs. Ah! will ſome poor ſouls ſay, precious Mr. <hi>Watſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Calamy,</hi> ſweet Mr. <hi>Venning,</hi> &amp;c. what is <hi>Paul,</hi> what is <hi>Apollo:</hi> what is Mr. <hi>Calamy,</hi> what is Mr. <hi>Watſon,</hi> but Miniſters by whom they believe: even as the Lord gave to every man: you plant, others water, God giveth the increaſe: ſo then neither is he that planteth any thing, nor he that watereth, but God that giveth the increaſe; tell me ſeriouſly whereas there is among you envying, and ſtrife, and diviſions, are you not carnal, and walk as men: for while one ſaith I am of <hi>Paul,</hi> and another I am of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo,</hi> and another I am of <hi>Cephas,</hi> are ye not carnal? O you can never receive the Word of God in the holy Ghoſt, in power, and in much <hi>aſſurance,</hi> while ye have mens perſons in admiration, &amp; receive the faith of God in reſpect of perſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 10 I am told you diſcourſed of the danger of looſing the Ordinances and Miniſtry of the goſpel. You know, Mr. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamy,</hi> we are in danger of looſing nothing, but what we never had until theſe twenty years: there is no more danger that I ſee, then that we are like to looſe thoſe novelties with which we have been troubled of late, that we may gain that ancient way, in which we have been happy, as you ſay, theſe hundred years (for I am told, that you ſaid, <hi>England hath enjoyed the Goſpel this hundred yeas:</hi>) Had <hi>England</hi> the Goſpel in the Epiſcopal, or in the Presbyterian way? after the Common-prayer, or after the Directory? with order and decency, or in diſorder and confuſion? Let all the world judge. Came the <hi>Goſpel from you to us,</hi> who all know are of yeſterday? or came it not unto you from us? We dare not make our ſelvas of the number, or compare our ſelves with ſome that commend themſelves; but they <hi>meaſuring themſelves by themſelves, and comparing themſelves among themſelves, are not wiſe</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12, 13, 14. We boaſt not of things without our mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that is, of other mens labours, only we hoped your ingenuity would have acknowledged, that the Goſpel Ordinances are not in any danger by your late removal; for you know you found Goſpel Ordinances here, when you came into the world, and, I hope, they may be found here after you are gone hence and are ſeen no more. O do a few Miniſters think, that their removing is the removing of the Goſpel! that it ſhould enter into a few
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53521:12"/>mens hearts that they uphold the Church: O if King <hi>Charles</hi> could ſay (when he was adviſed to grant what he could, to ſave, upon which he Church depended) <hi>God forbid that the Church of God ſhould depend upon a mortalman:</hi> O how much more may you ſay, that you were nouriſhed and brought up by the Church, and depended upon it, rather then it upon you: ſome indeed preach Chriſt out of contention, ſome you will ſay for gain notwithſtanding <hi>Chriſt is preached,</hi> and you may <hi>rejoyce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> 11. One reaſon they ſay you gave for Chriſtians care for the Ark was their love to the place of Gods preſence, but do your people love the habitation of Gods houſe, or rather this or that perſon that miniſtre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h there; do they deſire to dwell in the houſe of God, to ſee the beauty of the Lord, or to hear a friend judge you? oh theſe things ought not to be: If they love the Church, it is as it was theſe many years, if they love a party, we know what you mean by the Ark.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 12. <hi>You ſaid,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> uſed to ſay, <hi>for Sion ſake I will not hold my tongue:</hi> O alas! Mr. <hi>Calamy,</hi> when the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, to which you they ſay, ſwore obedience, was ſubverted, when 3000. Orthodox men were ſilenced, ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred and undone; when the ancient worſhip of God was aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed which you once uſed, (for you know you and I were once of a judgment and practice) when the Church was in the greateſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that it hath been ſince the Reformation you were ſilent: now a few opinions of yours about a few garments, geſtures, words, and other ſmall formalities, are not allowed, a few men wedded to theſe opinions will not preach becauſe they are not allowed; you cannot be ſilent, <hi>be not deceived, God is not mocked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 13. They ſay you ſaid, <hi>a child of God was careful of the Ark becauſe of his intereſt therein;</hi> by his care we might know the children of God: here Mr. <hi>Calamy</hi> I am afraid poor ſouls may wreſt the Scripture to their own damnation: if you mean by the Ask of God, the Church of God with his Ordinances, after the primitive and univerſal, all good take care of it; and the King and Parliament at this time take care to eſtabliſh it: If you mean only your own way (as every party cry up their own way for the only way of God) and the way of others of the ſeparation, and make it a ſign of a Child of God to be careful of you. O Sir, what a ſtone of ſtumbling do you caſt before all the ages of the Church, where there was one that knew, much leſſe was care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53521:12"/>for this way. But I hope you will not ſay, <hi>Then it is a certain ſign there were but few or none that were the children of God in thoſe ages.</hi> O Sir, to be of a Religion that ſaves only a party, is not a ſign of the Child of God, but of a man of contention. O let me live and die in that Religion, which (if not neglected) may ſave the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 14. You ſaid I am informed, That <hi>the Ordinances of God are the treaſures of a Chriſtian, and the loſſe of them cannot but trouble them.</hi> The Ordinances of God are Reading, Hearing, Sacraments and Prayer. Common prayer in a wholeſome form of ſound words, to which all could ſay <hi>Amen;</hi> was neglected for mens private notion, to which very few could ſay <hi>Amen:</hi> Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was quite diſufed, preaching the Goſpel was turned to the preaching of Opinions and Parties, and the Sacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme allowed to few, and that of the Lords Supper denyed almoſt to all (O <hi>Ely</hi> would have trembled at theſe things) the wayes of <hi>Sion,</hi> God knows, mourned, the ancient Miniſters of Chriſt were driven into corners, and were you troubled? did you lay it to heart? theſe are reſtored, what alles you now?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 15. Chriſt Jeſus you ſaid is the joy of Chriſtians, and therefore when Chriſt is departing they cannot but be much troubled at it. O Mr. <hi>Calamy,</hi> take heed of perſwading people, that the advancing of this or that party is the advancing of Chriſt, or that the diſcountenancing of them is the departing of Chriſt. If any man ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o, here is Chriſt, or there, or here he is departed, or there. O teach poor people, not to believe them, for there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe prophets, and ſhall <hi>ſhew</hi> great ſigns and wonders, inſomuch that (if it were poſſible) they ſhall deceive the very <hi>Elect.</hi> And I pray teach them where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if they ſhall ſay unto you, behold, he is in the deſert, go not forth, behold, he is in the <hi>ſecret chambers,</hi> or meetings, believe it not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 16. The people of God you ſaid were much troubled becauſe of the miſery of a nation when the Ark is departed. A Gentleman to whom words of this nature were communicated, and I am loath to write this of my ſelf, that where is you ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <hi>be to that nation when the Ark is gone,</hi> ſaid, <hi>wo be to that nation where the Ark of Presbytery, for its followed and attended with war, ſedition, bloud, ruine and confuſion,</hi> and O that ſad experience did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm this in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and other places. Inſomuch that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53521:13"/>the foreign Churches the men of Aſhdod of the Ark ſay, <hi>this way</hi> ſhall not abide with us, let it be carried about to Gath to other Churches, as <hi>Scotland,</hi> and in thoſe places it was attended with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great deſtruction, and they ſend it to <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> cried out, they have brought this way hither to ſlay us, and our people: and the King, Lords, and Commons in Parliament ſay, ſend this way to its own place, that it <hi>ſlay us not,</hi> and <hi>our people,</hi> for there was a deadly deſtruction throughout the whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try that came along with it, and the hand of God was very heavy here. And the cry of the Countrey went up to heaven, <hi>deſtruction and miſery, ſaith he, is in their way, and the way of peace have they not known.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 17. I was glad indeed to hear you ſay, <hi>That the people of God muſt needs tremble when the Ark is in danger, becauſe of their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarineſs to the looſing of the Ark;</hi> for to deal plainly with you, is the Church in danger? your diſturbances cauſe it: doth Popery break in upon us? the breaches you made upon Law and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment open the way to it: doth prophaneneſſe prevail? O you have made ſerious holineſs odious by goodly pretences and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy practices: doth not the Magiſtrate watch over Papiſts? Its becauſe your dangerous attempts makes him wholly intent upon you: doth he indulge them? you ſay men muſt have liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of conſcience: do we want Miniſters? why did you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw your ſelves? is the nation divided againſt it ſelf? who hath occaſioned it? have we loſt our firſt love? why do you by depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the firſt Reformation cauſe us to looſe our firſt love? <hi>Do the people run beadlong</hi> to the Garlick and Onions of <hi>Egypt?</hi> you mean Popery: and have not you forced them to do ſo, by crying down every thing that was eſtabliſhed for Popery, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have nothing upon which they may ſettle themſelves, but Popery: if they ſtay with us, they are in <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſay your party: if they go over to you, you are antichriſtian ſay the poor Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines: where ever they are in an orderly eſtabliſhed way, they are in Popery: and if all that is orderly and ſettled be Popery, to hear Papiſts we will go: if all decent worſhip, and regular Government be Popery, the Popiſh people ſhall be my people, &amp; their God ſhall be my God; where they die, I will die and there be buried: do poor diſcontented ſouls deſire to return to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> Is it not becauſe they of the ſeparation ſay there is no true Church in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:53521:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 18. But you were plain it ſeemes at laſt, and told them <hi>it muſt not be denyed, but the Arke was in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be loſt,</hi>— If you meane Presbytery, which we never had eſtabliſhed, there is no harmedone,— If you meane the Church of <hi>England</hi> with her Doctrine, Diſcipline, Worſhip, Rites and Ceremonies as eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by Law, it's well you have forewarned us, the King and Parliament I hope will take you at your words, and will take care to ſecure the Church upon ſuch foundations, as the Gates of Hell cannot prevaile againſt; well Sir I leave with you that of <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3.11. with you; He hath made every thing beautifull in his ſeaſon, yea he hath ſet the World in thine heart, ſo that no Man can find out the work that God maketh from <hi>the begining to the end,</hi> who know what is good for a Man in this life, all the dayes of his vaine life which he ſpendeth as a ſhadow, for who can tell a Man what ſhall be after him under the Sun; the thing that hath been it is that which ſhall be; and that which is done is that which ſhall be done: and Sir there is no new thing under the Sun, is there any thing whereof it may be ſaid be hold this is new? it hath been already of old Time which was before us: Mr. <hi>Calamy</hi> I know whatever God doeth it ſhall be for ever; nothing can be put to it, nor any thing taken from it; and God doth it that men ſhould fear before him. <hi>That which hath been is now, and that which is to be hath already been, and God requireth that which was paſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 19. I was informed you told your people that in <hi>their own concernments they were very ſenſible: But in the concernments of Religion very careleſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you intended to raiſe a ſedition (which I hope you did not, I am ſure the providence of God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver called you to it) you could not take a better courſe then to add to civill grievances which you
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53521:14"/>know the people murmure againſt Religious jealouſies and feares: O when Religion which ſhould reſtraine the multitude provokes them to ſedition, to what exceſſe of riot do they run; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Naz. <hi>inde furor vulgo</hi>—its naturall for men to think nothing little in the caſe of Religion; ſo that they can hardly perſwade themſelves, they can be angry enough in the caſe of a Diety—a diſcreet man will never ſtirre up the people in the defence of any point of Religion,—for their force when ſtirred up will deſtroy all religion: you know the late popular tumults were not ſo eaſily ellayed as they were raiſed by you; you know when the multitude had ſerved your hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours in pulling down Epiſcopacy, they ſerved their in overthrowing you.—</p>
            <p>It's more proper to tell the people of their duty then of their danger: our buſineſſe is to diſcover to the people the ſtate of their ſouls; let thoſe that are in Authority ſhew them the ſtate of the Government <hi>as who attend upon this very thing;</hi> and for the people—<hi>let them ſtand ſtill, and ſee the ſalvation of God;</hi>—let them peaceably walk with God, and God will watch over them—let them keep Religion every one in his heart, and Religion will keep its ſelf in the Church.—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 20. I hear <hi>you ſaid</hi> We <hi>had enjoyed the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell theſe hundred yeares</hi> and above? It's true we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned the Goſpell theſe 1400. yeares (as we can make it appear againſt the Papiſts from the ſeveral men that in all ages were eminent for their adherence to the Word of God, and to the Teſtimony of <hi>Jeſus:</hi> And truly I would not have the Papiſts hear that we have a Goſpel only of an hundred year old;) but it's as true that you were never contented under the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>We have had the Goſpel theſe hundred yeares, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53521:14"/>yet we have had admonitions, ſupplications, warnings, propheſyings,—remonſtrances ever ſince—you have never been contented ſince we left Popery; and if you gone complying with the Popiſh underminings whoſe great deſigne is by our diviſions to bring us back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; you will never be quiet untill we return to Popery againe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 21.
<q>
                  <hi>When I was told how you challenged any Scholler to ſhew where any Nation enjoyed the Goſpell for an hundred yeares together;</hi>
               </q> it put me in mind of a witty Gentlemans anſwer to one that asked, <hi>what</hi> if a Papiſt ſhould aske a <hi>Presbyterian where his Religion was</hi> 200. <hi>year ago?</hi> he might anſwer I <hi>know no more where it was two hundred year ago, then where it will be two hundred year hence:</hi> but (not to allow my ſelf even a ſober mirth on ſo ſad an occaſion) this puts me in mind of Biſhop <hi>Halls</hi> ſolemne offer: That if any man living can ſhew any one lay Presbyter that ever was in <hi>the World till</hi> Farell <hi>and</hi> Viret, <hi>or any Presbyterian Diſcipline till Mr.</hi> Calvin <hi>ſet one up,—let</hi> me (ſaith he) forfeit my reputation to ſhame, and my life to juſtice.—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 22. A wicked, prophane, drunken Miniſtry you ſay will never ſettle the Arke—you ſay; others ſay an envious, ambitious, ſeditious, unlearned, facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, will never ſettle the Arke, you would not hear the one, O ſpeak not the other: if you had known any ſuch, you had done well to tell <hi>them</hi> of it that they might amend; and not the people that they might be incenſed, this publique cenſuring and backbiting may <hi>provoke</hi> thoſe that do amiſſe, it will never reforme them;—this had been better told the Magiſtrate who might regulate the Miniſtry, and not the people, who (as you know and have at other times complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) being too much prejudiced againſt them which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53521:15"/>take this occaſion to have them the more: would to God (Mr. <hi>Calamy</hi>) you could bear with us a little in our folly; and indeed bear with us: I demand in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy who have been ſo diſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted,
<q>ſo diſconntenanced, ſo dejected, ſo deſpiſed, ſo deſolated, ſo depreſſed, wherein did they come ſhort of the beſt of Presbyters, were Presbyters good Preachers ſo were they before them; were Presbyters able Writers—they more; were Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters devout Men, ſo are they; were Presbyters zealous oppoſers of Popery ſo were they; were Presbyters of unblamed lives ſo are they;—were Presbyters Martyrs—they more; were Presbyters Inſtruments in the firſt juſt and orderly reformation they more; were Presbyters hospitable and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, they more;—who was more down-right then Biſhop <hi>Latimer?</hi> more holy then <hi>Hooper?</hi> more ſevere then <hi>Farrar;</hi>
               </q> more Grave then Arch-Biſhop <hi>Parker;</hi> more pious then <hi>Grindall;</hi> more candid and charitable then <hi>Whitgift;</hi> more pious and prudent then <hi>Bankroft;</hi> more holy and moderate then <hi>Abbat;</hi> more publique ſpirited then <hi>Laud,</hi> who was more Venerable then Biſhop <hi>King;</hi> who a greater Schollar and better Man then Biſhop <hi>Andrews;</hi> who more vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and judicious then Biſhop <hi>Lake;</hi> who more profound then Biſhop <hi>White;</hi> who more moderate then Biſhop <hi>Overall;</hi> who more exact then Biſhop <hi>Davenant;</hi> who more uſefull then Biſhop <hi>Field;</hi> who more honeſt then Biſhop <hi>Bilſon;</hi> who more Saintly then Biſhop <hi>Fetton;</hi> who more devoutly then Biſhop <hi>Carleton;</hi> who more conſcientious then Biſhop <hi>Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe;</hi> who more meek and peaceable then Biſhop <hi>Hall;</hi> who more innocent then Biſhop <hi>Patter;</hi> who more honeſt then Biſhop <hi>Winniffe;</hi> who more renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned then Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher;</hi> who more excellent then Dr.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53521:15"/>
               <hi>Himmond;</hi> who more meek, holy and judicious then Mr. <hi>Hooker;</hi> who more Heavenly then Mr. <hi>Lyford, &amp;c.</hi> who more compleit then Biſhop <hi>Brownrig.</hi> Not the thouſands more living and dead in our memory; ſome ſpots we have among us and ſo have you; ſome miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carrages, and they that have not let them throw the firſt ſtone at us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 23.
<q>You added (I am told) theſe expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the reſt, O that God would encourage our Nobles and Magiſtrates, that they might be ſolicitous to ſettle the Ark:</q>— Your meaning here Mr <hi>Calamy</hi> is as the Arke under a <hi>covering,</hi>— the King and his Nobles in Parliament have ſetled the Arke, Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the Church, would you have the Nobles unſetle them again,— the Government is ſetled, would you have the Nobles oppoſe it? what a Barons Warre, we never heard of a ſettlement theſe hundred yeares that you were ſatisfyed with; <hi>O when will it once be?</hi>—yes, you would be contented, but that the Ark is ſet in the Houſe of <hi>Dagon,</hi> whom you call Dagon we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as the God of our Fathers in the Lord Jeſus Chriſts as for the Dagons of <hi>Popiſh Images,</hi> and of new <hi>Imaginations,</hi> with which indeed our Ark is incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed, we hope to ſee them fall down ſuddainly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Ark; the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, Orthodox in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, devout in Worſhip, orderly in Ceremonies, ſtrict in Diſcipline, and <hi>ſafe</hi> under Authority; and here we ſet up our Pillar of gratitude with the ſacred Inſcription, <hi>Hitherto the Lord hath helped us,</hi> onely I ſhall leave with you theſe Queſtions to be reſolved as in the light of God for the ſatisfaction of your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which you have by this action at leaſt diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and of the Nation, whoſe peace and tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity you have diſturbed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Queſt.</hi> Whether you do not think in your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53521:16"/>(as you have often declared) that the Church of <hi>England</hi> is a true Church, enjoying all Ordinances and Priviledges neceſſary to mens ſalvation.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Queſt.</hi> If ſo, (as you all confeſſed) whether the Ark, which you ſay is a Type of the true Church, be not a Type of the Church of <hi>England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Queſt.</hi> The Ark being a Type of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whether it be now in danger, being newly eſtabliſhed by publick Authority.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Queſt.</hi> If it be in danger as now eſtabliſhed, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this danger proceeds not from your open oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and private endeavours againſt it; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be juſt in you to create the Churches danger, and then increaſe it by ſuggeſting to the people feares and jealouſies of its being in danger?—</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Queſt.</hi> Whether or no you ought in Conſcience to put us to theſe dangers only for few opinions, which none own but your ſelves, and your ſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood not an hundred year agoe; or againſt a few Ceremonies and points indifferent, which your ſelves ſubmitted to <hi>twenty</hi> yeares agoe.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Queſt.</hi> And indeed whether the Church of the Living God doth ſo depend upon a few mortal Men, ſuch as you are who lately left the Miniſtry, that upon the removal of a few ſingular Men it is in danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loſt; or if it doth ſo far depend upon them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they could in Conſcience hazard the ruine of the Church, rather then declare that they diſown the former miſcarriage, and they would lead peaceable and quiet lives under the preſent Government; If there had been enjoyned a great thing, would they not have done it? much more when they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded onely to <hi>Waſh and be Cleane?</hi> and to ſerve God (as ſome of them had done) as decently and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly as their Brethren.—</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:53521:16"/>
            <p n="7">7 <hi>Que.</hi> Whether now with twenty yeares feares jealouſies, and imaginations, we have been almoſt run out of all Religion, Church, Ordinances, and publick Tokens of the viſible of God, the Nation had not beſt reſolve to lay aſide all private ſuggeſtions, and to proceed to ſuch a ſtable ſettlement, as that we may ſay Return to thy Reſt O Lord with the Ark of thy ſtrength.</p>
            <p>Well Maſter <hi>Calamy,</hi> there will come a time when three words uttered with meekneſſe and charity ſhall receive a far more bleſſed reward, then three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Volumes written with diſdainfull ſharpneſſe of wit, and with malicious partiality; you are a man Maſter <hi>Calamy,</hi> you may erre and miſtake, your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline may be ſuppreſſed, ſome opinions of yours may be diſowned; you may be laid, and yet the Church of God ſtand upon the Foundation of the Prophets, and Apoſtles, and Paſtors, Jeſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe being the Corner-Stone:—</p>
            <p>Thus much I thought became the reſpects I always beared you, and the kindneſſe I had for your far for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſobriety and moderation; for indeed Sir I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your affectionate Friend in our common Saviour, <hi>O. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>dall.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
